Finding Aid for James T. Wilson papers, 1940-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James T. Wilson papers 1940-1978
Wilson, James T. (James Tinley), 1914-1978.
1.5 linear foot
85441 Aa 2
Professor of geology, and director of the Institute of Science and Technology at the University of Michigan. Files relating to his professional career, especially his interest in seismology and investigations into earthquake reduction; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers came from the Office of Science and Technology of the University of Michigan (donor no. 5993 ) in May 1984.
The collection is open to research.
James Tinley Wilson was born in Claremont, California on November 13, 1914, the son of Raleigh and Mary Brooks Wilson. He was educated at Porterville Junior College, and the University of California, Berkeley. (A.B. 1935, geology; Ph.D. 1939, seismology). He studied under Professor Perry Byerly.
In 1940, Wilson came to the University of Michigan as an instructor in the Geology Department. During the war, Wilson and his wife Martha Wheeler (married 1943) went to Mineola, Long Island, where Wilson joined Columbia University's Division of War Research. He helped work on some of the earliest forms of sonar.
After the War, the Wilsons returned to Ann Arbor. By 1955, Wilson was appointed Professor of Geology. The following year he became the Chairman of the Department, a position he held until 1961. In 1960, he joined the Institute of Science and Technology (IST) as associate director. Two years later he was made acting director, and became the director in 1964. Under his leadership the IST expanded greatly, especially in its interdisciplinary programs.
Wilson's interests were primarily in seismology, particularly in the areas of earthquake reduction and the monitoring of (underground) nuclear explosions. He was best known for his work on the effects of crystal structure upon the dispersion of Rayleigh and Love Waves.
Wilson was involved in numerous professional societies, some of which included the Seismological Society of America (Vice-President 1959, President 1960), the American Geophysical Union (President of the Seismology Section, 1974), the Geological Society of America, the Earthquake Engineering Research Institute, and the Royal Astronomical Society.
Wilson had a heart attack and died suddenly on May 25, 1978.
The papers of James Tinley Wilson consist of 1.5 linear feet of manuscript, photographic and printed material covering the years, 1940-1978. There is material from most aspects of Wilson's professional activities, but nothing relating to his private life.
The papers of James Tinley Wilson are most valuable as supplementary to other archival materials available at the Bentley Historical Library. Of most importance are the records of the Institute of Science and Technology. Unfortunately, as an independent research source, the usefulness of the collection is more limited. The full span of Wilson's professional life is documented, but not in any great depth. Researchers interested in the development of seismology as a field of scientific endeavor would possibly find Wilson's papers helpful, but those seeking information about any of the professional associations or the workings of the IST should be aware of the sparseness of these records.
The papers have been arranged in the following series: Biography, Associations, Conferences, Consulting, Correspondence, University of Michigan, Writings, Photographs.
Subjects:
Earthquakes.; Geology.; Seismology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute of Science and Technology.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Airplanes.; Cheboygan County (Mich.); Great Lakes Foundation.; Laboratories.; Military art and science.; Monroe County (Mich.); North Campus (University of Michigan); Project Michigan.; Radar.; Remote sensing.; Seismological Society of America. Eastern Section.; United States. Army.; University of Michigan. Biological Station.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute of Science and Technology.; University of Michigan. Willow Run Laboratories.; Wilson, James T. (James Tinley), 1914-
Genre Terms:
Aerial photographs.; Photographs.
- Biography
  The Biography series contains several curriculum vitae, a news release about Wilson's appointment as Director of the IST and several eulogies.
  - Miscellaneous vitas, etc. (Box 1)
- Associations
  The associations represented in this series are all professional organizations of which Wilson was a member. These have been arranged alphabetically. Numerous associations are included, but except for the Council on Institutional Cooperation (CIC) there is not much material on any of them.
  - Advanced Research Projects Agency (Department of Defense) 1960-1966 (Box 1)
  - American Geological Institute
    - General 1961-1968 (Box 1)
    - Visiting Scientist Program 1962-1970 (Box 1)
  - American Geophysical Union, Seismology Section 1962-1975
    - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (CIC) 1963-1969 (Box 1)
    - Account Information (Box 1)
    - Economic Growth, Committee on (Box 1)
    - Economic Growth, Technology and Public Policy, Council on (Box 1)
    - Ice Formation Control, Meeting on (Box 1)
    - Programs
      - Ocean Sciences (Box 1)
      - Summer Study on Systems Model on the Great Lakes (Box 1)
      - University-Industry Relations (Box 1)
      - Water Resources (Box 1)
  - Earthquake Engineering Research Institute 1973-1977
    - General (Box 1)
    - Committee on Strong Motion (Box 1)
  - Great Lakes Foundation Trustees (Box 1)
  - International Union of Geodesy and Geophysics 1957-1964
    - General (Box 1)
    - 12th Congress, Helsinki 1960 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Basin Geological Society 1974 (Box 1)
  - NASA-Manned Space Science Geophysics Working Group 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - National Research Council
    - Computer Usage, Committee on (Box 1)
    - Earthquake Reduction, Task Force on (Box 1)
    - Gas Reserve Estimates (Box 1)
    - Panel Remote Sensing of Environment, Committee on, and Subcommittee on Declassification (Box 1)
    - Seismology, Committee on (Box 1)
    - Strong Motion Seismology, Panel on (Box 1)
  - Royal Astronomical Society 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Seismological Society of America 1960-1975 (Box 1)
  - Society of Exploration Geophysicists 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Theta Tau 1972 (Box 1)
  - U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey 1962 (Box 1)
- Conferences
  The Conferences series documents Wilson's involvement in a number of professional meetings and symposia. The series includes related correspondence as well as copies of speeches and papers given by Wilson.
  - 1961
    - National Academy Society-National Research Council Conference (Box 1)
  - 1962
    - Michigan Industry-University Space Age Research Conference (Box 1)
  - 1963
    - Dedication of Data Analysis Center, Washington, D.C. (Box 1)
    - American Ordnance Association Combat and Tactical Division (Box 1)
    - Geophysical Service Inc.-Annual Earth Science Orientation Session (Box 1)
  - 1965
    - Electromagnetic Sensing of the Earth from Satellites symposium (Box 1)
  - 1967
    - Conference on Engineering Seismology. (Box 1)
    - Symposium on Astrogeology (Box 1)
    - National Conference on Technology Utilization and Economic Growth (Box 1)
  - 1968
    - Uppsala Symposium on the Management of Large Lakes and Impoundments (Box 1)
    - Great Lakes Water Research Conference (Box 1)
    - National Classification Management Society (Box 1)
- Consulting
  In addition to his teaching, Wilson did a fair amount of "free lance" work. The Consulting series contains correspondence between Wilson and his clients, as well as some of his own field notes, maps, and reports. The series is organized alphabetically by client.
  - Bryant Family Estate 1941-1954 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Edison
    - 1955 Zug Island Site (Box 1)
    - 1955-1958 Lagoona Site (Box 1)
    - 1956-1958 Monroe Site (Box 1)
  - Diamond Alkali Company 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Employers' Group Insurance Companies 1955 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Accident and Indemnity Company 1958 (Box 1)
  - McHenry, James 1956 (Box 1)
  - Mammoth Cave (Box 1)
  - Michigan Vitrified 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - Power Reactor Development Company 1957-1960 (Box 1)
  - Schlee, McIntosh and Simpson 1957 (Box 1)
  - United States Senate, Subcommittee on Disarmament 1958 (Box 1)
  - University of California, Los Angeles 1974 (Box 1)
  - Wyandotte Clinker-Cooler 1956-1957 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Wilson's Correspondence is arranged chronologically. This is a fairly large series, running from 1960 to 1978. All of the correspondence is professional.
  - 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - 1967-1972 (Box 1)
  - 1973-1978 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan
  The University of Michigan series is subdivided into "Conference on the University," "Institute of Science and Technology, and "School of Literature, Science and Arts - Geology and Mineralogy." This is a rather disappointing series. Although most of Wilson's professional life was spent at the University of Michigan, the material covering his activities there, both as a professor and as Director of the IST, is quite sparse.
  - Conference on the University May 18-19, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Institute of Science and Technology 1961-1977 (Box 1)
  - School of Literature, Science and Art, Geology, Department of and Mineralogy
    - Camp Davis (Box 1)
    - Earthquakes (Box 1)
    - Graduate Students (Box 1)
    - Personnel (Box 1)
    - Seismograph Station
      - Construction (Box 1)
      - Operation (Box 1)
- Writings
  The Writings consist of reprints of his scientific articles, but also including several reviews, a memorial essay about Professor Perry Byerly, and a proposal written for the Air Force Office of Scientific Research.
  - Reprints
    - 1940-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    - 1964-1974 (Box 2)
  - Reviews 1961-1976 (Box 2)
  - Others 1964-1978 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes portraits; aerial photographs of Monroe County, Michigan, the University of Michigan's Biological Station, Cheboygan County, Michigan, and the North Campus area of the University; and photographs of radar projects done in conjunction with the U.S. Army at Willow Run Airport and other sites.
  - Portraits (Box 2)
  - Willow Run facility (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    (include aerial view of North Campus of the University of Michigan)
  - Department of Defense, Project Michigan photographs, 1 volumes (Box 2)